Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
- Series V: American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee/United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency, undated, 1946-1950; Box 6, Folders 1-6.
  - UNRRA Specialist - Displaced Persons, 1944-1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Route Slip from Olive Sawyer to Razovsky., October 28, 1945 and December 2, 1946; 2 copies. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      She has corrected her payments. Attached is a Personnel Journal signed by Lyman H. Cozad, Personnel Officer, UNRRA. The journal is a corrected copy of Razovsky's reinstatement from LWOP and transfer. Razovsky's position has changed from Displaced Persons Specialist, Division of Displaced Persons to Consultant, Office of Public Information. Her headquarters are in Washington, D.C.
    - Letter from E. Masour, Oeuvre de Secours Aux Enfants to Razovsky, AJDC, New York., January 9, 1946; In French. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letter from Harriet P. Clark, Secretary to James G. McDonald to Razovsky, 17 Park Avenue, New York, New York., January 10, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Clark attaches a letter dated January 8, 1946 from the World Encyclopedia Institute that is addressed to McDonald. The F. Kaufman, Managing Editor of the World Encyclopedia is requesting an article on the "Refugee Problem." He wishes the article to begin historically at the Russian Revolution of 1917, and to concentrate on the Jewish aspect of the "refugee problem." Attached are letters between M.J. Nurenberger, World Encyclopedia Institute and McDonald concerning deadlines for the article that will appear in a one volume titled "The Jews." A handwritten note from H.P. Clark to Razovsky was unable to provide Razovsky with the information she needed. (see Box 6, Folder 3, Item #1)
    - Copy of letter from Clara Balter, Area Secretary, NCJW, New York to Tillie Davis, AJDC, New York., January 22, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Davis has requested excerpts from NCJW Vice-President Mrs. Albert and NCJW President of Providence Section Mrs. Rouslin regarding their desire to have Razovsky speak in Providence, RI on February 19, 1946.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Helen Kohn, AJDC, Prague, Czechoslovakia., January 20, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Razovsky updates Kohn on her news. She and Davidson have returned from Brazil where she wrote a "long report on conditions there" for refugees. Razovsky is sending items Kohn needs and has asked that Kohn contact a "dear friend" of hers, Rosa Pelantova, Assistant Mayor of Prague.
  - AJDC, February 1946-October 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Travel authorization signed by Assistant Adjutant General Frederick W. Faerber, Jr., February 23, 1946; 2 copies. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is traveling under UNRRA auspices from Paris, France to Frankfurt, Germany for 9 days.
    - Authorization to purchase money orders signed by Harry D. Biele, Deputy Director for Germany, American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee., undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky holds the position of Director of Emigration for Germany for the AJDC.
    - Railway pass, signed by Maurice Barber, Executive and Military Liaison Officer., February 23, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      For Razovsky's trip from Paris, France to Frankfurt, Germany.
    - Letter from Joseph E. Beck, Executive Director of the NRS to Razovsky., February 28, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Beck appoints Razovsky as a representative of the NRS in the American occupied zone in Europe. Attached is a copy of a letter from Razovsky to the Personnel Division, UNRRA, February 10, 1946. Razovsky has been working as a consultant for the Public Information Division of UNRRA. She is resigning from this position as of February 14, 1946 to work overseas with the American Joint Distribution Committee.
    - Travel authorization, signed by Ida Lee Reynolds, UNRRA Travel Section., March 2, 1946; 3 copies. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is attending a Conference on immigration work of Voluntary agencies, and is traveling from Frankfurt to Munich for five days.
    - Travel authorization, signed by V.D. Phillips, Travel and Accommodation Section, UNRRA., March 20, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is traveling from Arolsen to Frankfurt, Germany for 26 days to work on "immigration problems."
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to AJDC., April 2, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      The letter details an automobile accident Razovsky had on March 10th on her way to Arolsen, Germany. She has spent several weeks in the hospital.
    - Copy of medical report signed by Murray N. Levin, Chief of Surgical Service., April 4, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Details her injuries and requests that her husband, who is in Paris, be allowed to visit her.
    - Copy of travel authorization, signed by R.G. Rayment, District Director UNRRA and W.G. Ratcliffe, Jr., 1st. Lt., April 13, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky and Dorothy Levy will be traveling from Wiesbaden to Berlin, Germany for approximately three weeks under AJDC auspices.
    - Authorization to purchase money orders, signed by V. Coucheron-Jarl, Liaison Officer, UNRRA., April 16, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Copy of travel authorization, signed by R.G. Rayment, District Director UNRRA and W.G. Ratcliffe, Jr., 1st. Lt., April 29, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky, Levy, and Jacques Oettinger, all AJDC staff, are traveling from Wiesbaden to Bremen, Germany for approximately three weeks.
    - Travel authorization signed by Ida Lee Reynolds, UNRRA Travel Section. Razovsky is traveling from Frankfurt to Bremen, Germany for nine days in order to supervise financial arrangements for emigrants departing to the United States., May 6, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Memorandum from Razovsky., May 20, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Memorandum provides statistics, financial arrangements, and general conditions for the passengers sailing to the U.S. on SS Marine Flasher and SS Marine Perch.
    - Hotel accommodations authorization signed by John W. Gould, 2nd Lt., for Dr. Davidson., June 11, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Travel authorization signed by Nora Price, UNRRA Travel Section., June 12, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is traveling from Frankfurt to Bremen, Germany for five days to supervise immigration AJDC programs.
    - Pages 3, 7, and 8 of untitled report by Razovsky., undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Report by Razovsky., June 20, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Memorandum from Razovsky to AJDC Paris and New York., June 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky lists her clothing that was destroyed in the automobile accident. (See Item #7 and Item #8)
    - Memorandum from Razovsky., June 20, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Memo concerns the history of two passengers, an uncle and his supposedly orphaned niece, who sailed on SS Marine Flasher. The girl's father was located and is awaiting the granting of his visa.
    - Memorandum from Razovsky to AJDC Paris., June 21, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky asks for additional injuries she sustained in her automobile accident to be reported to the insurance company. (See Item #7, Item #8, and Item #18)
    - Travel authorization signed by B.J. Edwards, Personnel Officer, UNRRA., June 29, 1946; 2 copies. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is traveling to Frankfurt, Germany.
    - Report by Razovsky., July 5, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Memorandum provides statistics, financial arrangements, and general conditions for the passengers sailing to the U.S. on SS Marine Flasher.
    - Travel authorization signed by Nora Price, UNRRA Travel Office., July 10, 1946; 2 copies. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is traveling from Frankfurt, Germany to Paris, France for five days to attend the AJDC Conference on Immigration.
    - Receipts from the War Department's Finance Department, signed by J.M. Jones. Lt. Col., May 9, 1946 and July 12, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Receipts for accommodations for Razovsky and Davidson.
    - Letter from Ann Petluck, Director Migration Department, NRS to Razovsky., July 15, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Petluck discusses a memorandum Razovsky wrote to Philip Bernstein advising an extension of visas to refugees in British and French zones.
    - Travel authorization signed by Nora Price, UNRRA Travel Office., July 29, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky is traveling from Frankfurt to Munich-Stuttgart, Germany for five days in order to conference with AJDC personnel.
    - Travel authorization signed by Joseph W. Whitaker, Captain and R.C. Raymond, UNRRA District Director., August 9, 1946; 3 copies. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Razovsky will be traveling from Wiesbaden to Paris, France for five days to attend an immigration conference.
    - Memorandum from Helen Tannenbaum, AJDC to all Emigration Offices., August 8 and 17, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Attached is a letter dated August 8, 1946 from Ann S. Petluck, United Service for New Americans, to Razovsky, concerning Razovsky's advice on plans for aged displaced persons who have no relatives to help them in the United States.
    - AJDC Report No. 384., October 8, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Report of Harold Nordlicht, J.D.C. Representative in Linz, Austria from May to September 1946.
    - Letter from Lester Schnurman, Acting Chief Accountant to Razovsky., October 8 and 15, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Letter concerns Razovsky's insurance claim. Attached is a copy of a letter from Razovsky to Schnurman. She will fill out the application form Schnurman requests once she has received hospital reports. (see Item #7, Item #8, Item #18, and Item #20)
    - Letter from J.W. Fairchild, Chief of Payroll, UNRRA to Razovsky., October 10, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Fairchild mailed Razovsky's Provident Fund check in February. Attached is a copy of a letter from Razovsky to UNRRA, September 25, 1946. She resigned from UNRRA on February 15, 1946 and requests her Provident Fund entitlements. Attached is a form signed by Lyman H. Cozad, Personnel Officer, UNRRA, noting Razovsky's employment information and her rights to Provident Fund entitlements.
  - Background Material on Life in DP Camps, undated, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Copy of report by James G. McDonald. "Refugees.", January 1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Possibly the article on refugees requested by the World Encyclopedia. (See Box 6, Folder 1, #59.)
    - Address by Rabbi Philip S. Bernstein, at the Biltmore Hotel, New York City., October 1, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Rabbi Bernstein is taking a leave of absence from his congregation Temple B'rith Kodesh, Rochester, New York to assist displaced persons. There are currently two hundred thousand displaced persons, "infiltrees from Eastern Europe." He expresses appreciation to the Jewish agencies and United States government officials involved in helping refugees. He examines the relationship between the military and displaced persons. He writes of survivors of the Kielce pogrom in Poland who are in a hospital in Lodz. Knowing a large amount of refugees will be fleeing Poland, Bernstein describes the difficulties in obtaining European government help. "My heart is heavy as I report that not a single government in Europe has been prepared to offer more that temporary shelter to these people." He continues by addressing approaching problems, includes statistics of displaced persons in allied zones (total is 218,201 ), and states "Palestine is the major hope... I can assure you that they will brave every hardship and every danger to settle in Palestine..."
    - Letter from Edna W. Goldman, Search and Emigration, AJDC, United States Forces Austria to Razovsky, AJDC, New York., November 21, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Attached is correspondence between Goldman, other AJDC staff and Razovsky regarding Sabina Bochner who is at Camp Wegscheid in Linz, Austria. A camp address handwritten by Bochner is attached to one of the letters.
    - Telegram from Arthur Greenleigh to unknown., undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Greenleigh writes of child refugees from Buchenwald and Hillersleben who have arrived in France. (See Box 6, Folder 2, Item #30.)
    - Translated copy of statement from Juedischer Hilfsausschuss, Buchenwald to Jewish Community, Geneva., undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      The statement is a request outlining current problems to forward to Jewish relief agencies. The survivors' request information about survivors, help with relatives' contacts, obtaining personal identification documents, procurement of immigration authorization and transportation costs, regulation of nationality questions, and placement and care for orphans.
    - Report, unsigned. "Terezin.", undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Report of the Nazi occupation of Terezin, "designated by the Nazis in the early stages of the so-called Protectorate as the Ghetto of the Czechoslovak Jews." There were 35,000 Jews in Terezin when Germany surrendered. Prior to the surrender, Nazis "dumped the most miserable, diseased and humiliated prisoners of other concentration camps," who were mostly political non-Jewish prisoners, in Terezin. Handwritten note from Joseph W. Eaton asking "where are the JDC representatives? Where are people from the Jewish agency? It is about time they come here and take a hand!"
    - Report, unsigned. "Living Conditions of Jews in the Protectorate.", undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Nazis promised that the Nuremberg laws would not be imposed upon Czechoslovakia. New Czech laws have emerged that are "Nuremberg laws in paraphrase."
    - Report by Sam Herman, Gary Indiana. "Memorandum on the Jews in Germany.", undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Herman served as Director of UNRRA and supervised the displaced persons in Eastern Bavaria to the Czechoslovakian border in May 1945.
  - AJDC - Brazil (September-December 1946), undated, 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet, "Sociedade Beneficente Israelita do Rio de Janeiro.", September 18, 1945; 2 copies. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlet, translated and published by British Chamber of Commerce in Brazil. "Complete Text of the Brazilian Immigration Legislation.", January 28, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Copy of telegram from Luis Lorch, São Paulo, Brazil to Benjamin B. Goldman, AJDC New York., September 9, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Lorch requests a Yiddish female speaker "maybe Razovsky" to address women to help with their annual campaign.
    - Copy of letter from B.F. Pollack to Asociacion Filantropica Israelita in Uruguay., September 13, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Copy of letter from B.F. Pollack to Asociacion Filantropica Israelita in Uruguay., September 17, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mildred G. Walt, President NCJW New York., September 25, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky acknowledges Walt's letter (attached) and accepts Walt's invitation to be a speaker at the 18 th NCJW Triennial Convention.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to George Warren, International Migration Service., September 25, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      She has just returned from Germany and will be going to Brazil for the JDC on October 6th. She asks if there is any work available for her in his organization upon her return.
    - Invitation from Associacao de Socorro aos Israelitas de Wolin, Simhat Torah., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky will make a presentation.
    - Boletim S.O.S. Campanha de 1946, Comite Auxiliar do Joint, No. 1., September 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Invitation from Mr. and Mrs. David H. Brandon, for a reception in honor of Razovsky and her co-speaker Rabbi Isaiah Rackovsky, AJDC representatives., October 6, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Invitation from Comite Auxiliar do Joint de São Paulo., October 23, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky will be a speaker, representing the AJDC.
    - Invitation from Congregacao Israelita Paulista, São Paulo., October 24, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky will be a speaker.
    - Copy of letter from Robias Berelejis, Encargado de Difusion to Junta Israelita de Socorro en Cooperacion con el Joint, Uruguay., October 24, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letter and copy of letter from J.B. Lightman, American Delegate, AJDC, Buenos Aires, Argentina to Razovsky., October 30, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      A new unexpected wave of immigrants came to Brazil while Razovsky was there. He asks when she will be arriving in Argentina; he would like to discuss with her the immigration between Europe and South America.
    - Invitation., November 3, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letter, unsigned, to Erwin Rosen, AJDC, Paris, France., November 5, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Relatives in Porto Alegre Brazil will be forwarding documents to AJDC France to enable their families in Poland and Germany to immigrate to Brazil. The letter asks immediate and efficient assistance.
    - Copy of letter from J.B. Lightman, American Delegate, AJDC, Buenos Aires, Argentina to AJDC New York, November 7, 1946., October 25, 1946; October 31, 1946; November 7, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Lightman writes of negotiations for the distribution and funding of immigration work in Uruguay between the Junta and Afilantis. A copy of an unsent cable from Lightman concerning the above is attached. Also attached are copies of letters: one dated October 31, 1946 from Leon Friedheim, Secretary, Asociacion Filantropica Israelita del Uruguay to the President of Junta Israelita de Socorro and another dated October 25, 1946 from Luis Goldstein, President and Erwin Schnurman, Secretary, Junta to Comision Directiva de la Afilantis.
    - Summary, unsigned., November 7-26, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      A summary of Razovsky and the author's visit to Rio Brazil, where only one meeting had been scheduled. Razovsky spent much of her time trying to organize women committees. There are discrepancies between various groups within the Rio Jewish community, however; all contribute generously when solicited for funds. In general, not enough "careful preparation" had been done to allow workers to help in the funding campaign. Typewritten on the back of Morris Davidson's stationery.
    - Letter from Lupes ?, São Paulo, Brazil, to Razovsky, Rio de Janeiro., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Lupe thanks Razovsky for her and Dr. Davidson's visit to her family and gives Razovsky the address of Dr. Gerhard Kahn in Bolivia.
    - Copy of letter from Tobias Berelejia, Encargado de Difusion to Luis Goldstein, President, Junta Israelita de Socorro en Cooperacion con el JOINT, Uruguay., November 8, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Edith Striemer, São Paulo, Brazil, to Razovsky., November? 20, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky has probably already left for New York, but Striemer hopes to make her acquaintance "my sister having told me often in her letters of your helpfulness and active friendship."
    - Letter from Henry H. Callius, Jr., City Hotel, Buenos Aires, Argentina, to Razovsky., November 26, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky is arriving to Buenos Aires tonight. Callius and Ralph K. Taylor are on an IGC mission to the River Plate Countries and are in Argentina for a few days and would like to talk to her.
    - Copy of memorandum from Irwin Rosen, Director AJDC New York to AJDC Buenos Aires, Argentina., November 27, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Memorandum concerns the transportation of immigrants from Europe to the Dominican Republic.
    - Letter from Larry Magrath, U.S. Maritime Commission, Frankfort to Razovsky., November 27, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      "Life here is just as complicated as ever, brought about largely by the continual disruptions to our schedule due to strikes and ships delayed by engine trouble, etc. At this time, we have had no ships since October 12 and now have 2100 people at Bremen with hundreds more in the Emigrant Assembly Centers with only one vessel in sight between now and the end of December..."
    - Letter from Sara E. Stein, AJDC Munich to Razovsky., October 21, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Stein updates Razovsky on the current situation for DPs in Germany. There are currently 132,000 Jews in Germany compared to 91,000 in July and will be 140,000 more by the end of the year. She asks Razovsky to stress the need for DPs immigration to South America, and requests information on the Jewish communities in South American countries. A handwritten message dated December 1, 1946 to Razovsky is below. The letter was returned to Sara Stein and then resent. Stein notes that Razovksy must have returned to New York by now.
    - Copy of letter from J.B. Lightman, American Delegate, AJDC, Buenos Aires, Argentina to AJDC New York. Razovsky visit to his office was "very worthwhile." He recommends Razovsky stay on in Brazil for two or three more months to help organize a regional bureau in Brazil to be set up in Rio in order to help strengthen the Comite Auxiliar there., December 2, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Razovsky, Comite Auxiliar do Joint no Rio de Janiero to Donna Luisa Lorch. Razovsky gives Lorch an address for a possible candidate for a social worker position in São Paulo., December 6, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Carlota Wolff, Comite Auxiliar do Joint no Rio de Janiero, to Razovsky., December 8, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Report by Razovsky. "Emigration to Brasil and the Argentine.", December 9, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum from Razovsky to Mr. Selig and Mr. Monte., December 19, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Razovsky lists recommendations she gave to J.B. Lightman regarding funds for emigration work in Brazil.
    - Letter from Carlota Wolff, Comite Auxiliar do Joint no Rio de Janiero, to Razovsky., December 26, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Carlota would be delighted to work with Razovsky and Davidson again and hopes that they reached New York safely.
    - Copy of letters from Razovsky to Ernesto Feder, William Selig, Maxim Sztern and others in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil., March 20, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      An introductory letter to Reta L. Stein who is arriving in Brazil as a AJDC representative. Attached is the address of a good hairdresser and a good curio shop in Rio, as well as a list of female volunteers in social work.
    - Excerpts from report of Rio visit, unsigned, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Report, unsigned., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Report by Carlota Wolff, pages 2 and 3., undated; 2 pages. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Report of Brazil visit by Razovsky., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Report includes campaign notes, immigration work, and statistics of Rio arrivals from April to September.
    - Campaign flyer with telegrams of refugees' names and a list of funds contributed to the Joint from 1914 to 1946., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Campaign flyer., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - List of cooperating agencies in Central and South America., 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - UNRRA Child Search Reports, February-May 1947 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Press release from UNRRA Public Information Office, Munich?, Germany. "UNRRA Child Welfare Service.", July 1946 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Summary of search work performed by the service. Once a child is found, they are moved to a UNRRA Children's Center. Other children who are with their parents live in DP camps where educational and recreational programs have been arranged for them.
    - Press release from UNRRA Public Information Office, Heidelberg, Germany., February 15, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Czech children, found by the UNRRA, were discovered mostly in German homes where they were placed for "Germanisation and possible adoption by on [sic] SS child-placing organization. The others were in orphanages, monasteries, and similar German institutions..." Story of Lidice, Czech children. Individual child cases are summarized.